export const questions = [
    {
      question: "What is Narsil?",
      options: ["A Ring", "A Sword", "A Settlement in Eriador", "A Hobbit Delicacy"],
      correct: "A Sword",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Aragorn is an heir to which kingdom?",
      options: ["Angmar", "Rohan", "Rhûn", "Gondor"],
      correct: "Gondor",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Which of the following is Gollum's original name?",
      options: ["Otho", "Sméagol", "Meriadoc", "Fredegar"],
      correct: "Sméagol",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "What is Samwise Gamgee's trade?",
      options: ["Gardener", "Guard", "Farmer", "Grocer"],
      correct: "Gardener",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "What was the main goal of Thorin Oakenshield and his Company?",
      options: ["Aquire the Arkenstone", "Plunder the dragon hoard", "Reclaim the dwarven kingdom Erebor", "Rescue the King of Durin's Folk"],
      correct: "Reclaim the dwarven kingdom Erebor",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "What is Smaug?",
      options: ["Dragon", "Eagle", "Balrog", "Werewolf"],
      correct: "Dragon",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "How is Éowyn related to Théoden, king of Rohan?",
      options: ["Daughter", "Niece", "Cousin", "Grandchild"],
      correct: "Niece",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Black Riders are also known as...?",
      options: ["Ainur", "Valar", "Avari", "Nazgûl"],
      correct: "Nazgûl",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "What is the name of the region ruled by Galadriel?",
      options: ["Rivendell", "Eregion", "Lothlórien", "Mordor"],
      correct: "Lothlórien",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Denethor II was the ruler of Gondor. What was his title?",
      options: ["King", "Emperor", "Stewart", "Count"],
      correct: "Stewart",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Which one of the hobbits participated in the Battle of the Pelennor Fields along with Éowyn?",
      options: ["Merry", "Pippin", "Sam", "Bilbo"],
      correct: "Merry",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Moria used to be a...?",
      options: ["Mine", "Dwarven kingdom", "Cave", "Tomb"],
      correct: "Dwarven kingdom",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "What is special about the sword Sting?",
      options: ["It glows blue in the presence of orcs", "It was created by Vala Aulë", "It absorbs the life force of the target and gives it to the wielder", "It was specifically made for killing giant spiders"],
      correct: "It glows blue in the presence of orcs",
      difficulty: 1
    },
    {
      question: "Other name of Rivendell",
      options: ["Imladris", "Anor", "Umbar", "Mirkwood"],
      correct: "Imladris",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "After the War of the Ring, Gimli founded a new dwarven colony near the Helm's Deep. What was this colony called?",
      options: ["Menegroth", "Glittering Caves", "Erebor", "Kahazad-dûm"],
      correct: "Glittering Caves",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "In the books, Frodo sold Bag End and purchased a property in Buckland called...?",
      options: ["Crickhollow", "Bywater", "Underhill", "Tuckborough"],
      correct: "Crickhollow",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "When returning from their quest to destroy the ring, Frodo and his companions found Shire to be...?",
      options: ["As it was before leaving", "Controlled by Saruman and his ruffians", "Burned to the ground", "Protected by Dúnedain of the north"],
      correct: "Controlled by Saruman and his ruffians",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "Which of the following is NOT true about Tom Bombadil",
      options: ["The Ring of Power has no effect on him", "He saved Frodo and the other hobbits from Barrow-wights by singing", "He did not participate in the War of the Ring", "He is one of the Valar"],
      correct: "He is one of the Valar",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "Who saved Frodo from the Black Riders by chasing them away and sending him to Rivendell on hers/his horse?",
      options: ["Arwen", "Sam", "Glorfindel", "Gandalf"],
      correct: "Glorfindel",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "Who of the following did NOT go to Valinor",
      options: ["Gimli", "Arwen", "Sam", "Legolas"],
      correct: "Arwen",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "How do Elven Rings differ from other Rings of Power?",
      options: ["They were not under the control of The One Ring", "They did not lose their power after the One Ring was destroyed", "They amplify bearer's natural skills", "They were created without the help of Sauron"],
      correct: "They were created without the help of Sauron",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "At his coronation, how old was Aragorn?",
      options: ["38", "58", "88", "108"],
      correct: "88",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "What is the capital of Mordor?",
      options: ["Barad-dûr", "Utumno", "Angband", "Taur-im-Duinath"],
      correct: "Barad-dûr",
      difficulty: 2
    },
    {
      question: "Elrond had a twin brother, what is his name?",
      options: ["Elrohir", "Elladan", "Elros", "Eärendil"],
      correct: "Elros",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "How was Arda, the universe, created?",
      options: ["It is a byproduct of an explosive clash between Melkor and Ilúvatar", "It is a reflection of the Ainur's collective consciousness", "Ilúvatar conjured it with Secret Fire", "By Music of the Ainur"],
      correct: "By Music of the Ainur",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Círdan the Shipwright is the oldest named elf in Middle-earth. How old was he in the Lord of the Rings?",
      options: ["3000 years", "5500 years", "8800 years", "11000 years"],
      correct: "11000 years",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Why did the last king of Númenor, Ar-Pharazôn, go to war against the Valar?",
      options: ["To gain immortality", "To free his people from the oppression of the Valar", "To gain valuable resources not available anywhere else", "To gain the power of creation through Flame Imperishable"],
      correct: "To gain immortality",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Who is the One, creator of everything?",
      options: ["Ilúvatar", "Morgoth", "Fëanor", "Elbereth"],
      correct: "Ilúvatar",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "What happened to Petty-dwarves?",
      options: ["They were hunted to a point of extinction by Sindar elves", "Morgoth conquered their lands and enslaved them", "They migrated to the Dark Land and allied themselves with Sauron", "Over thousands of years they slowly evolved into hobbits"],
      correct: "They were hunted to a point of extinction by Sindar elves",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Who created the Silmarils, Palantíri, and the elvish writing system among other things?",
      options: ["Finwë", "Fingolfin", "Fëanor", "Finarfin"],
      correct: "Fëanor",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "How did Morgoth lose one of the Silmarils on his crown?",
      options: ["It dropped in a duel with Fingolfin", "Lúthien put Morgoth and his whole court to sleep with her dance and took it", "Ungoliant overpowered him with her unlight and took one", "Thorondor pried one off while retrieving body of a fallen friend, scarring Morgoth's face"],
      correct: "Lúthien put Morgoth and his whole court to sleep with her dance and took it",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Who created the dwarves?",
      options: ["Ulmo", "Aulë", "Ilúvatar", "Melkor"],
      correct: "Aulë",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Why did Gondolin fall?",
      options: ["Majority of the population perished in the Kinslaying", "Ilúvatar destroyed it by flood", "An elf led Morgoth's army there", "It was infiltrated by Sauron in form of Annatar"],
      correct: "An elf led Morgoth's army there",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Tar-Minyatur was the first king of Númenor. What was his birth name?",
      options: ["Túrin", "Elros", "Beren", "Estel"],
      correct: "Elros",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "What are the 'Nameless things'?",
      options: ["Unspeakable atrocities committed by Morgoth in the First Age", "Offspring of Ungoliant", "Primordial entities dwelling in the deepest places", "Fallen Ainur worshipped by evil men of Nan Dumgorthin"],
      correct: "Primordial entities dwelling in the deepest places",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "What is a common misconception about balrogs?",
      options: ["They are Maiar", "They have wings", "They are affiliated with fire", "They serve Morgoth"],
      correct: "They have wings",
      difficulty: 3
    },
    {
      question: "Which of the following groups of elves are NOT part of the Moriquendi?",
      options: ["Teleri", "Sindar", "Laiquendi", "Avari"],
      correct: "Teleri",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "Where did the First Kinslaying take place?",
      options: ["Cuiviénen", "Alqualondë", "Havens of Sirion", "Doriath"],
      correct: "Alqualondë",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "After defeating the trolls, Gandalf, Bilbo and the dwarves found their hoard containing Glamdring among other things. Who was the original owner of Glamdring?",
      options: ["Tuor", "Túrin", "Turgon", "Thingol"],
      correct: "Turgon",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "Which one of these characters was inspired by Kullervo, a character from national epic of the Finns, Kalevala?",
      options: ["Tuor", "Boromir", "Túrin", "Aragorn"],
      correct: "Túrin",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "What are the names of the two blue wizards?",
      options: ["Alatar and Pallando", "Olórin and Curunir", "Ossë and Uinen", "Eönwë and Ilmarë"],
      correct: "Alatar and Pallando",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "Who is the herald of Manwë?",
      options: ["Melian", "Ilmarë", "Olórin", "Eönwë"],
      correct: "Eönwë",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "Galadriel's mother gave her a name 'Nerwen'. What does it mean?",
      options: ["Noble Woman", "Spirit of Fire", "Man-maiden", "Song of Gold"],
      correct: "Man-maiden",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "What is Dagor Dagorath?",
      options: ["Lieutenant of Morgoth", "A weapon forged from a meteorite", "War between Valar and Melkor before awakening of the elves", "An apocalyptic prophecy"],
      correct: "An apocalyptic prophecy",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "What was the first source of light in Arda?",
      options: ["Varda's stars", "Yavanna's Two Trees", "Arien's Sun", "Aulë's Two Lamps"],
      correct: "Aulë's Two Lamps",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "What was the main trigger for animosities between elves and dwarves?",
      options: ["Elven genocide of Petty-dwarves", "Murder of elven king Thingol by dwarves", "Dwarves awakening the balrog of Moria", "Elves conquering the lands of the dwarves and exiling them"],
      correct: "Murder of elven king Thingol by dwarves",
      difficulty: 4
    },
    {
      question: "What is the Common Speech in Middle-earth?",
      options: ["Quenya", "Adûni", "Khuzdul", "Dunlendish"],
      correct: "Adûni",
      difficulty: 5
    },
    {
      question: "In Tolkien's earliest drafts, Aragorn was depicted as ...?",
      options: ["A maia", "An elf", "A dwarf", "A hobbit"],
      correct: "A hobbit",
      difficulty: 5
    },
    {
      question: "How many solar years is one Valian year?",
      options: ["5.582", "7.852", "9.582", "13.285"],
      correct: "9.582",
      difficulty: 5
    },
    {
      question: "Who of the following is counted among the Aratar?",
      options: ["Morgoth", "Nienna", "Tulkas", "Estë"],
      correct: "Nienna",
      difficulty: 5
    },
    {
      question: "After Lord of the Rings, Tolkien began writing a sequel that was never finished. What is the name of the sequel?",
      options: ["The War of the Jewels", "The Lost Road", "The New Shadow", "The Last Battle"],
      correct: "The New Shadow",
      difficulty: 5
    },
    {
      question: "The Noldor elves used to be called...?",
      options: ["Gnomes", "Goblins", "Fairies", "Pixies"],
      correct: "Gnomes",
      difficulty: 5
    }
  ];